Guide to the John Hope Franklin papers, 1891-2010, bulk 1950-2010 RL.10029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings (W), 1934-2009 and undated; 43 boxes
  - Edited Works, 1947-2003
    - A Fool's Errand, by Albion Tourgee, publicity and correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box W30)
      Published in 1961 by Belknap Press.
    - Atherton Press consulting editor, 1965-1970 (Box W30)
    - Urban Negro American in the Twentieth Century, Chicago Urban League correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box W30)
    - Pamphlets in American History correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box W30)
    - Integrated Education Associates Advisory Board correspondence, 1965-1978 (Box W30)
    - Color and Race correspondence, 1964-1982 (Box W30)
      Published in 1968 by Hougthon Mifflin Co.
    - Reminiscences of an Active Life: The Autobiography of John Roy Lynch (1990), 1952-1974; 6 folders (Box W30)
      Published in 1970 by University of Chicago Press. The files contain drafts (two folders), the memorandum of agreement, correspondence (1952-1978), and reviews and publicity.
    - Negro American Biographies and Autobiographies, University of Chicago series, 1948-1980
      - "William Wells Brown," by William Farrison, 1967-1970 (Box W30)
      - Correspondence re: T. Thomas Fortune,1958-1973 (Box W30)
      - Correspondence re: William Pickens, 1971-1973 (Box W30)
      - Correspondence re: Anna J. Cooper, 1972-1977 (Box W30)
      - Correspondence re: James Weldon Johnson, 1971-1973 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence re: George L. Knox, 1976-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence re: Ida B. Wells, 1965-1981 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence re: Paul Cuffe, 1967-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence re: James T. Rapier, 1948-1978 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence re: Willard Motley, 1972-1973 (Box W31)
      - Henry O. Tanner correspondence and Franklin's forewords, 1967-1979 (Box W31)
      - General correspondence, 1967-1980 (Box W31)
    - Doubleday Zenith project, 1965
      - Project records (Box W31)
    - The New Deal McGraw-Hill series
      - Outline, undated (Box W31)
    - Black Leaders of the Twentieth Century, 1978-1982
      Published in 1982 by University of Illinois Press.
      - Correspondence and drafts, 1978-1982, 3 folders (Box W31)
      - Correspondence with Louis Harlan re: Booker T. Washington essay, 1979-1981 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on T. Thomas Fortune, by Emma Lou Thornburgh, 1979-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on Whitney Young, by Nancy Weiss, 1978-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on Malcolm X, by Peter Goldman, 1979-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on Ida B. Wells-Barnett, by Thomas Holt, 1979-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence with Darlene Hine on Mabel Staupers, 1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on Martin Luther King, Jr., by David Lewis, 1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence with Benjamin Quarles on A.P. Randolph, 1979-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on James Weldon Johnson, by Eugene Levy, 1979-1980 (Box W31)
      - Correspondence and drafts on W.E.B. DuBois, with Elliot Rudwick, 1979-1981 (Box W31)
      - Book reviews, 1982-1988 (Box W31)
    - American History series, 1963-2001
      Published by Harlan Davidson.
      - Promotional materials (Box W32)
      - Correspondence, 1963-2001, 11 folders (Box W32)
      - Prospectus, titles, proposed guidelines, 1972, 1977 and undated (Box W32)
      - Royalty statement, 1984 (Box W32)
      - Master list of proposed titles and authors, 1993 (Box W32)
    - Encyclopedia of Slavery contract and article list, 1994-1995, 2 folders
      - Contract and list (Box W32)
    - African Americans and the Living Constitution, 1988-1998
      Published in 1994 by Smithsonian Institution Press.
      - Drafts for symposium at the Smithsonian, 1988, 2 folders (Box W32)
      - Drafts for book, 1988-1993, 2 folders (Box W32)
      - Drafts for book, 1993, 2 folders (Box W33)
      - Contract, 1994 (Box W33)
      - Proposed table of contents (Box W33)
      - Correspondence, 1988-1998 (Box W33)
      - Book reviews, 1996-1997 (Box W33)
    - Buck C. Franklin: My Life and an Era, 1950-2001
      Published in 2000 by LSU Press. Co-edited with John Whittington Franklin. Additional materials, including Buck C. Franklin's diary, can be found in the Personal and Family Series.
      - Draft, undated, 3 folders (Box W33)
      - Chapter and section drafts, undated, 18 folders (Box W33)
      - Draft, undated (Box W34)
      - Research notes and materials, 5 folders (Box W34)
      - Correspondence with Buck C. Franklin, 1960 (Box W34)
      - Untitled manuscript, 2 folders (Box W34)
      - "The Path of Tears: A Story of the Removal of the Cherokees," by Peter Maytubby, undated (Box W34)
      - "States Rights in 1952?" by BCF, Tulsa Tribune, 1950 (Box W34)
      - "On the Chisholm Trail," undated (Box W34)
      - "Buck C. Franklin: Race and the Law in 20th Century Oklahoma," undated (Box W34)
      - "Buck C. Franklin, 1879-1960" (Box W34)
      - Correspondence, 1983-2000 (Box W34)
      - Publicity and book jacket, 1997 (Box W34)
      - Reviews, 1997-2001 (Box W34)
    - Tributes to John Hope Franklin (2003)
      Published by Cambridge University Press in 2003.
      - Correspondence, 2003 (Box W34)
  - Other Writings, 1942-2009
    - Travel Diaries, 1960-1979
      - Account, June 12-Sept. 2, 1960, 2 folders (Box W34)
      - Trip to China, Oct./Nov. 1979 (some pages missing), 3 folders (Box W34)
    - For Better, For Worse, 1999
      Co-written with Aurelia Franklin. Additional materials held in the Personal and Family Materials Series.
      - Drafts and materials re: publication, 1999 (Box W34)
      - Correspondence, 1999, 2 folders (Box W34)
    - Statements, 1989-2001 and undated
      - Various statements (Box W34)
    - Index Entries, 1963-1988
      - Index entries, various (Box W34)
    - Apologia Sua Vitae, undated
      - Draft (Box W34)
    - Interviews, 1976-2009
      Articles and transcripts from interviews of Franklin, largely from the 1990s and 2000s. Additional clippings and coverage of Franklin can be found in the Research, Biographical, and Subject Files Series.
      - National Endowment for the Humanities interview, Feb. 1976 (Box W34)
      - Interview by Bennet L. Singer, May 1978 (Box W34)
      - New York Times profile and reactions, Apr. 1995, 2 folders (Box W34)
      - Interview by Carl Polsgrove, 1997 April (Box W35)
      - First Person Singluar press kit, Rogers University, OK, June 1997 (Box W35)
      - Interview with Dorothy Jenkins Fields, Eckerd College, 1997 (Box W35)
      - "The Color Line: Stretching in the 21st Century," Humanities Interview, Spring 1997 (Box W35)
      - Interview with Hugh Price, National Urban League, 1998 (Box W35)
      - "Freedom and Free Land: The Black Settlement of Oklahoma," National History Day Project, 1998 (Box W35)
      - Souls Magazine interview and correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box W35)
      - Interview transcript, 1999 (Box W35)
      - WUNC TV Biographical Conversations, Feb. 2000, 2 folders (Box W35)
      - American Heritage interview with Leon Litwack, 2001-2002 (Box W35)
      - A Conversational History of Modern America, by Richard Heffner, 2003 (photocopy) (Box W35)
      - Interview for Public Historian, 2005-2007 (Box W35)
      - Journal of African American History oral history interview with Brian Purnell, 2009 (Box W35)
    - Book Reviews Written by Franklin, 1942-2000 and undated
      Files are arranged chronologically.
      Drafts, correspondence, and published versions of book reviews written by Franklin. The majority of the material predates the 1970s.
      - Free Negro Labor and Property Holding in Virginia, by Luther P. Jackson, 1942 (Box W35)
      - The Negro and the Post-War World: A Primer, by Rayford Logan, 1945 (Box W35)
      - Liberia, by Charles Morrow Wilson, 1947 (Box W35)
      - A Free Church in a Free State, by Frank Klingberg, and Church and State, by Evarts Greene, 1948 (Box W35)
      - The Development of Southern Sectionalism, by Charles S. Snyder, 1948 (Box W35)
      - Frederick Douglass, by Benjamin Quarles, 1948 (Box W35)
      - The Labor Force in Louisiana, by Rudolf Heberle, 1948 (Box W35)
      - Les Negriers, Ou le Trafic Des Esclaves, by Andre Ducasse, 1948 (Box W35)
      - The Dixie Frontier, by Everett Dick, 1948 (Box W35)
      - Achilles Heel of America: The Negro, by K.T. Behanan. 1949 (Box W35)
      - Romanticism and Nationalism in the Old South, by Rollin Osterweis, 1949 (Box W35)
      - Codrington Chronicle: An Experiment in Anglican Altruism on a Barbados Plantation, ed. by Frank Klingberg, 1949 (Box W35)
      - The Southern Colonies in the 17th Century, by Wesley Frank Craven, 1949 (Box W35)
      - The Negro in the United States, by E. Franklin Frazier, 1949 (Box W35)
      - To Be Free: Studies in American Negro History, by Herbert Aptheker, 1949 (Box W35)
      - Southern Legacy, by Hodding Carter, 1950 (Box W35)
      - Slavery in Alabama, by James Benson Sellers, 1950 (Box W35)
      - Society and Thought in Early America, by Harrey Wish, 1950 (Box W35)
      - Origins of the New South, by C. Vann Woodward, 1951 (Box W35)
      - The Mark of Oppression, by Abram Kardiner and Lionel Ovesey, and The Negro and the Communist Party, by Wilson Record, 1951 (Box W35)
      - Documentary History of the Negro People in the US, by Herbert Aptheker, and On Being Negro in America, by J. Saunders Redding, 1951 (Box W35)
      - Correspondence with the Journal of Negro Education re: reviews, 1952-1962 (Box W35)
      - The Missouri Controversy, by Glover Moore, 1953 (Box W35)
      - The Negro in the Civil War, by Benjamin Quarles, 1953 (Box W35)
      - The Growth of Southern Nationalism, by Avery O. Craven, 1953 (Box W35)
      - A History of the Southern Confederacy, by Clement Eaton, 1954 (Box W35)
      - The Suppression of the African Slave Trade to the USA, 1638-1870, by WEB DuBois, 1954 (Box W35)
      - Bleeding Kansas, by Alice Nichols, 1954 (Box W35)
      - The Negro People in American History, by William Z. Foster, 1954 (Box W35)
      - North Carolina: The History of a Southern State, by Hugh T. Leffler and Albert R. Newsome, 1954 (Box W35)
      - American Paradox: The Conflict of Thought and Action, by Merle Curti, 1956 (Box W35)
      - The Peculiar Institution, by Kenneth Stampp, 1956 (Box W35)
      - The Sable Arm: Negro Troops in the Union Army, 1861-1865, by Dudley Taylor, 1956 (Box W35)
      - DuBois and the NAACP, by Francis J. Broderick, 1957 (Box W35)
      - Slavery in Tennessee, by Chase C. Mooney, 1957 (Box W35)
      - The Negro in Indiana Before 1900: A Study of a Minority, by Emma Lou Thornbrough, 1957 (Box W35)
      - The Lonesome Road: The Story of the Negro's Part in America, by Saunders Redding, 1958 (Box W35)
      - 4 Reviews for the American Political Science Review, 1957-1958 (Box W35)
      - The Negro in North Carolina Prior to 1961, by James Boykin, 1958 (Box W35)
      - The Road to Harper's Ferry, by J.C. Furnas, 1959 (Box W35)
      - The Story of Reconstruction, by Hodding Carter, 1959 (Box W35)
      - Critiques of 'Voice in America' broadcasts on the Civil Rights Movement, 1960s (Box W35)
      - The Slave Trade, by Daniel P. Mannix, 1960 (Box W35)
      - Slavery: A Problem in American Institutional and Intellectual Life, by Stanley Elkins, 1960 (Box W35)
      - Why the North Won the Civil War: Economic Considerations, by Richard Current, 1960? (Box W35)
      - Race Relations in Virginia, 1870-1902, by Charles E. Wynes, 1961 (Box W35)
      - Antislavery: The Crusade for Freedom in America, by Dwight Lowell Dumond, 1961 (Box W35)
      - Blyden of Liberia, by Edith Holden, 1961 (Box W35)
      - Crusaders for American Liberalism, by Louis Filler, 1961 (Box W35)
      - The South Since 1865, by John Ezell, 1963 (Box W35)
      - Politics, Principle, and Prejudice, 1865-1866: Dilemma of Reconstruction America, by Lawanda Cox and John H. Cox, 1963 (Box W35)
      - The Mighty Revolution: Negro Emancipation in Maryland, 1862-1864, by Charles Lewis Wagandt, 1964 (Box W35)
      - The Troublesome Presence: American Democracy and the Negro, by Eli Ginzberg and Alfred S. Eichner, 1964 (Box W35)
      - The Struggle for Equality: Abolitionists and the Negro in the Civil War and Reconstruction, by James McPherson, 1964 (Box W35)
      - Who Speaks for the South, by James McBride Dabbs, 1964 (Box W35)
      - Mr. Lincoln's Proclamation: The Story of the Emancipation Proclamation, by Frank Donovan, 1964 (Box W35)
      - Report to the Society of American Historians re: several manuscripts, 1964 (Box W35)
      - Black Reconstruction in America, 1860-1880, by W.E.B. DuBois (paperback), 1964 (Box W35)
      - The Right to Vote: Politics and the Passage of the Fifteenth Amendment, by William Gillette, 1965 (Box W35)
      - The Era of Reconstruction: 1865-1877, by Kenneth Stampp, 1965 (Box W35)
      - Manchild in the Promised Land, by Claude Brown, 1965 (Box W35)
      - From Race Riot to Sit In, 1919 and the 1960s, by Arthur Waskow, 1965 (Box W35)
      - The Oxford History of the American People, by Samuel Eliot Morison, 1965 (Box W35)
      - Lee, by Clifford Dowdey, 1965 (Box W35)
      - Benjamin Lundy and the Struggle for Negro Freedom, by Merton L. Dillon, 1966 (Box W35)
      - George Washington Julian, Radical Republican: A Study in 19th Century Politics and Reform, by Patrick Riddleberger, 1966 (Box W35)
      - The Confessions of Nat Turner, by William Styron, 1967 (Box W35)
      - The Buffalo Soldiers: A Narrative of the Negro Calvary in the West, by William Leckie, 1967 (Box W35)
      - David Walker's Appeal in 4 Articles, ed. By Charles M. Wiltse, 1965 (Box W35)
      - Slavery, Race, and the American Revolution, by Duncan J. MacLeod, 1974 (Box W35)
      - Orchids: Flowers of Romance and Mystery, by Jack Kramer, 1975 (Box W35)
      - Adam Clayton Powell, Jr.: The Political Biography of an American Dilemma, by Charles V. Hamilton, 1991 (Box W35)
      - One Blood: The Death and Resurrection of Charles Drew, by Spencie Love, 1996 (Box W35)
      - Cassius M. Clay and Southern Abolitionism, by David Smiley, undated (Box W35)
      - Reader's Report for Preserving the Nation: The Conservation and Environmental Movements, 1870-2000, by Tom Welleck, undated (Box W35)
    - Forewords, Afterwords, and Introductions, 1954-2006 and undated
      Files are arranged chronologically by publication year.
      Drafts and correspondence between Franklin, authors, and publishers over his contribution to various books.
      - Black Moses, by David Cronon, University of Wisconsin Press, 1954 (Box W35)
      - Army Life in the Black Regiment, by Thomas Wentworth Higginson, 1958-1962 (Box W35)
      - Up from Slavery, 1962-1963 (Box W35)
        Correspondence only.
      - W.E. Burghardt DuBois, Pioneer Historian of the Slave Trade, Louisiana State University Press, 1969 (Box W35)
      - The Great Ones, Washington Square Press, 1970 (Box W35)
      - The Past Before Us: Contemporary Historical Writing in the United States, ed. By Michael Kammen, 1980 (Box W35)
      - Introduction to National Push for Excellence Program, 1981 (Box W35)
      - Black Initiative and Government Responsibility, Committee on Policy for Racial Justice, 1987 (Box W35)
      - Emancipation Proclamation introduction, National Archives and Records Administration, 1986, 1993 (Box W35)
      - 100 Years of Fisk University Presidents foreword, 1989 (Box W35)
      - "Visions of a Better Way, A Black Appraisal of Public Schooling" preface, 1989 (Box W35)
      - Boston Abolitionist Project introduction, drafts and correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box W35)
      - Carter G. Woodson Project correspondence and foreword, 1993 (Box W35)
      - Preface to the Inclusive University: A New Environment for Higher Education, Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies, 1993 (Box W35)
      - Foreword to Hine Sight: Black Women and the Re-construction of American History, by Darlene Clark Hine, 1994 (Box W35)
      - One Blood: The Death and Resurrection of Charles R. Drew, 1995-1996 (Box W35)
      - Black Intellectuals: Race and Responsibility in American Life, by William M. Banks, 1996 (Box W35)
      - Democracy Betrayed, by David Cecelski and Tim Tyson, 1998 (Box W35)
      - Black Psychiatrists and American Psychiatry, by Jeanne Spurlock, 1999 (Box W35)
      - The Rich Heritage of African Americans in North Carolina, 1999-2000 (Box W36)
      - When Public Housing was Paradise, by Jimmy Fuerst, 2003 (Box W36)
      - Bridges of Memory, by Timuel D. Black, April 7, 2003 (Box W36)
      - Toward Humanity and Justice: The Writing of Kenneth B. Clark, 2004 (Box W36)
      - Earl B. Dickerson: A Voice for Freedom and Equality, Northwestern University Press, 2005 (Box W36)
      - Legacy: Treasures of Black History, National Geographic Society, Inc., 2006 (Box W36)
      - African Americans at Duke University, untitled, undated (Box W36)
    - Eulogies, Dedications, Nominations, and Tributes, 1965-2003
      Files are arranged alphabetically by last name.
      Personal essays and notes written by Franklin in honor of his friends and colleagues.
      - Apperson, Lillie Mae Congleton, 1896-2003 (Box W36)
      - Aptheker, Fay; Aptheker Herbert, "Remembering Herbert and Fay Aptheker, August 5, 2003 (Box W36)
      - Bennett, Lowell Howard, 1913-1993 (Box W36)
      - Bond III, John P., "Prescient Leader, Cherished Friend" in memory of John P. Bond III, August 20, 2001 (Box W36)
      - Brown, Walter, foreword to Brown's Biography (Box W36)
      - Clark, Kenneth Bancroft, eulogy, 2005 (Box W43)
      - Currier, Theodore S., 1903-1979 (Box W36)
      - Edmonds, Helen, tribute (Box W36)
      - Farrar, Eleanor, "Best of friends," eulogy, Sept. 2005 (Box W43)
      - Franklin-Jones, Mozella, "Loving Caring Sister", Remarks at the Funeral of Franklin's Sister, Tulsa, OK, April 9, 1986 (Box W36)
      - James, Henrietta Crawley, Eulogy, Fisk Memorial Chapel, March 29, 1968 (Box W36)
      - Johnson, Walter, Contribution to Walter Johnson Memorial, 1983-1987 (Box W36)
      - Logan, Rayford, Quotation from Rayford Logan, eulogy, 1982 (Box W36)
      - Logan, Rayford Whittingham, 1897-1982 (Box W36)
      - Lucas, Ernestine Garrett, "A Meditation on Ernestine Garrett Lucas", December 8, 2005 (Box W36)
      - Moran, Julius Augustine, 1914-1965 (Box W36)
      - Myers, Mrs. James A., 1878-1968 (Box W36)
      - Pierce, Bessie, Tribute (Box W36)
      - Robinson, Armstead Louis, "The Gift of Armstead Louis Robinson, September 29, 1995 (Box W36)
      - Quarles, Benjamin, An Appreciation, 1996 (Box W36)
      - Ray, Charles, "A Testament to Friendship", February 9, 1986 (Box W36)
      - Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent (Box W36)
      - "Thorpe: Taught and Self-Taught", undated (Box W36)
      - Tutu, Desmond, Nomination of Desmond Tutu for "Reflections of Hope" Award (Box W36)
      - Wall, Bennett H., First Christian Church, Athens, GA, September 8, 2003 (Box W36)
      - Watts, Charles de Witt, eulogy, Durham, 2004 (Box W43)
      - "Words of Reflection on the Life of a Dear Friend", June 27, 1992 (Box W36)
    - Undated Outlines
      Outlines created by Franklin for various projects, including speeches, articles, and essays. Some files have no known title.
      - Loose pages and untitled notes from various works (Box W36)
      - "The North Achieves Victory", undated outline (Box W36)
      - "Howard Bell-Negro Convention Movement", undated outline (Box W36)
      - "What the Teaching Historian Looks for in a State Historical Agency", undated (Box W36)
      - "Windows on the World", undated, untitled outline (Box W36)
      - "DuBois: Problem of the 20th Century", undated outline (Box W36)
      - "SNAP is to be Congratulated", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Conditions in 1865", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Lincoln and the Problems of Today", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "How Radical was Reconstruction?", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Historical Truth in a Democracy", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Everything is Relative", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "World War II: The Aims and Policies of Franklin D. Roosevelt", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Five Fables", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Caste and Politics: Implications for an Educated Democracy", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Schools and Democracy", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "The Moral Roots of Race Relations", undate outline (Box W37)
      - "Problems of Adjustments to Freedom", August 19, 1964 (Box W37)
      - "The Supreme Court and Civil Rights", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Protests and Demonstrations in a Democratic Society", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Caste and Politics in the Post-Reconstruction Era", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Building a World Community", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Reconstruction and Race Relations", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Jim Crow", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Participation of Blacks in the Gulf War", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "America, The World, and Race", undated outline (Box W37)
      - Untitled handwritten notes (Box W37)
      - Untitled notes, 1997, 1998 and undated (Box W37)
      - Untitled biographical notes (Box W37)
      - Handwritten bibliographic and autobiographical notes (Box W37)
      - "From Slavery to Freedom: The Place of the American Negro Today", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Jefferson on a Free Press (1823)" and "Freedom of Speech and Press in the U.S.". Undated outlines (Box W37)
      - Untitled, undated outline (Box W37)
      - "The American Dilemma and World Opinion", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Validating the Constitution: The Civil Rights Movement", undated outline (Box W37)
      - Untitled, undated history of "Negro" (Box W37)
      - "From Slavery to Freedom: The Place of the American Negro Today", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "The Role of Historical Societies in the U.S.", undated outline (Box W37)
      - "Continuing Implications of the Monroe Doctrine", undated outline (Box W37)
      - Notes on writing a memoir, "In the footsteps of history," undated (Box W43)
    - Lists of Publications and Permissions to Reprint, 1981-1993
      - List of Lectures and Writings since 1981 (Box W37)
      - Bibliographic Information, re. Franklin and CV (Box W37)
      - Lists of Publications by Franklin (Box W37)
      - Permissions to Reprint, 1981-1993 (Box W37)
  - Restricted Writings
    Some speeches and articles written by Franklin are restricted and require permission from the Franklin family prior to use. Titles are listed below. For more information and to request access, contact Research Services.
    - "America's Negro Fighters," Hampton Institute, Jan. 31, 1948 (Box W40)
    - Aspects of the Black Revolution, Portuguese translation, 1953 (Box W40)
    - "Reconstruction," in Problems in American History, ed. by Arthur Link and Richard Leopold, Prentice-Hall Series- correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box W40)
    - "Reconstruction," in Problems in American History, ed. by Arthur Link and Richard Leopold, Prentice-Hall, Author's Agreement, 1956 (Box W40)
    - "Reconstruction," in Problems in American History, ed. By Arthur Link and Richard Leopold, Prentice-Hall, correspondence, 1956-1973 (Box W40)
    - "These Things We Know," Washington DC, June 9, 1955 (Box W40)
    - "Sectionalism and the American Historian," International Congress of Social Sciences, Rome, Aug. 1955 (Box W40)
    - "Sectionalism and the American Historian," International Congress of Social Sciences, Rome, 1956 (Box W40)
    - "The Southern Expansionists of 1846," Journal of Southern History, Vol. 25, no. 3, Aug. 1959 (Box W40)